Ramakrishna Nalla

+1 (424) 625 5275

ramakrishna.nalla@gmail.com

FULL STACK ENGINEER

SENIOR ENGINEER • TECHNICAL LEAD • SPECIALIZED IN DESIGNING WEB APPLICATIONS

Comprehensive background in modern industry-adopted JS technologies for large-scale enterprise initiatives.

Full Stack Architect and Engineer with decades of comprehensive experience in modern Front-end frameworks and developing rich user experience for critical enterprise applications. Developed a customer service chatbot using the OpenAI API to automate 80% of common inquiries. Solid understanding of view layout and rendering technologies. Extensive experience in web-based applications and high-level proficiency in JavaScript, React, Angular, Node, HTML, and CSS technologies. Demonstrated strengths in building APIs using Node, REST, and GraphQL APIs. Experienced with Web Application Architecture for optimized performance. Designed and architected 2000+ React and Angular components. Experience in working with a large team of developers, QA Engineers, and scrum masters. Experience in building CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins, Docker, and custom scripts. Proven ability to effectively plan, coordinate, and meet deadlines, and business expectations for medium to large-scale projects.

TECHNICAL PROFICIENCIES

Angular • React-Redux-Hooks • Node JS • RxJS • Single SPA MFE • ExpressJS • Jest• Jasmine • Karma • Open AI • AWS GraphQL • RESTful API • Apigee • HTML • CSS Frameworks • SASS • Style • Build Tools • Babel • TypeScript • WebPack CICD • Docker • Git • MongoDB • Agile Scrum • SAFe • Jira • Rally • Adobe Photoshop • Invision• Figma

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Marsh Insurance, Phoenix, AZ

2020 - Present

Lead Engineer and Architect - LINQ Application (2020 - Present)

Technical Lead, integral member, and developer for an Enterprise Web Application of 3000+ clients. Charged with providing hands-on across all full-stack initiatives in application development with performance. Led all project functions, including requirements analysis, development, sprint planning, and stakeholder communication. Ensure successful project/feature completion within an Agile environment.

- Led the onsite, and offshore development teams and successfully partnered with the geographically dispersed support teams to resolve high critical front-end issues.
- Collaboratively worked with business, and Google teams for analytics and map integration.
- Designed, architected, and collaborated in developing Angular application with 200+ reusable components
- Built 50+ ReST APIs using Node, MongoDB, and secured APIs with JWT token and Apigee layer.
- Integrated DataDog, Sonar, and white hat, Sysdig, Git Guardians tools for to scan and analyze vulnerabilities, and code issues and guide the team to fix them.
- Led MFE development for React and Angular. Implemented 20+ GUI dashboards using amChats and D3 is.
- Developed OKTA SSO using OAuth 2.0 OIDC and integrated it with Marsh-connected Apps.
- Partnered with cross-functional technical teams to improve web security and accessibility standards.
- Championed 30+ major change initiatives and promoting continuous improvements in code quality, reviews, versioning, and deployment process.
- Collaborated with external agencies for developing feature managed web applications. which resulted in smooth and on demand feature releases.
- Closely working with the team and hands-on on fixing 250+ critical bugs in the application to improve performance and user experience.

American Express Technologies, Phoenix, AZ

2010 - 2019

Senior Web Developer -Instant Card Number (2016 - 2019)

An integral member of the Enterprise Web Application charged with providing hands-on across all front-end initiatives in application development, performance, RWD, accessibility, and redesigns using React and Angular tech-stacks.

• Led the front-end development and collaboratively worked with **Google** and **Samsung** teams for Digital wallet integration

- Designed, architected, and wrote the front-end of ICN application using AngularJS with 8,00+ reusable components
- Built a fully scalable SPA (Single Page Application) application for more than 50k user traffic. The application generated more than \$2M worth of revenue for American Express
- Implemented RUM scripts, Splunk dashboard, and API performance metrics using in-house tools.
- Created CI/CD pipeline using Jenkins and custom scripts; WebPack build and GIT workflow optimizations
- Successfully partnered with the geographically dispersed support teams to resolve high critical front-end issues.
- Collaborated with external agencies like Digitas, and Space 150 for developing high performing web applications for American Express which resulted in a growth of 5% incremental card acquisitions

AMERICAN EXPRESS, Phoenix, AZ/New York, NY

Technical LEAD/Front-end Developer - US Digital Acquisition, Card Shop & Card App (2015 - 2016)

Charged with the role of a Technical-Lead for end-to-end front-end development. Bridged the gap between back-end engineering and offshore departments by leading/participating in daily stand-ups, driving change management, and leveraging technical acumen through all project phases.

Technical LEAD/Front-end - US Digital Acquisition, CCSG, OPEN, and API (2010 - 2015)

- An integral member of \$5M annual digital marketing program; built web application and supported a team of 12 offshore resources.
- Spearheaded the first mobile site development of a 1.2M project. Led the offshore team and collaborated with UI/UX, back-end, and test engineers from the project inception through rollout.
- Achieved 50% better scores for google page-speed, yslow and XpressScan, by implementing performance standards
- Resolved 250+ critical bugs in the application to improve performance and user experience.
- Developed acquisition experience for the partner integration with Amazon Prime, designing and deploying system enhancements, as well as introducing new technologies to integrate the application within the partner's infrastructure.

Additional Experience:

AMERICAN EXPRESS - Junior Web Developer - US Digital Acquisition CCSG

2007 - 2010

Successfully contributed to the complete redesign of the UI of the application. Developed a componentized UI framework using JQuery, AJAX, Zepto, Moo tools, DOJO frameworks

- Delivered a solid, bug-free high-performance code with active collaboration with QA Engineers
- Mentored team members on front-end design, development, and performance.

NEFTA Solutions - Software Engineer

2004 - 2006

Contributed to developing Servlets and JSP page to redesign applications and was involved in analyzing and fixing production bugs.

Areas of Excellence

Experience architecting large-scale multi-tier web applications, Experienced with MEAN and MERN Stack, Agile Development, GIT Workflow, Creative Problem Solving & Analytical Skills, Quick Learner, Commitment, Motivator, and Mentor.

EDUCATION

KAKATIYA UNIVERSITY, INDIA - Master of Computer Applications

Professional Development & Awards

Received Client Appreciation from American Express in Q1 – 2010, 2011, 2014, 2019 Certified Scrum Master (CSM) & Product Owner Certified Flash MX Developer